Guide to the Barbara Hammer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Barbara Hammer papers
1940-2017
GEN MSS 1482
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
51.33
(73 boxes)
The Barbara Hammer Papers, which span from 1940 to 2017, contain writings, research materials, and documentation related to Hammer's films and artwork including Nitrate Kisses, Resisting Paradise, and Lover Other. The papers also contain correspondence, clippings, ephemera, audiovisual materials, and electronic media related to her life and work.
Hammer, Barbara
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 46-66 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 67-68 (born digital): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Barbara Hammer, on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 2017.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Writings and Personal Papers, 1940-2017. II. Teaching Notes, 1970-2010. III. Film Projects, Artwork, and Research, 1980-2017. IV. Audiovisual Materials, 1974-2015. V. Electronic Media, 1997-2014. VI. Costumes, Clothing, and Acccessories, 1979-2015.
Barbara Hammer
Barbara Hammer (1939-) is a filmmaker, visual artist, and teacher. Born in Hollywod, California, Hammer has created over eighty films and videos during her career, including her most well-known work, "Nitrate Kisses." Hammer's film, photography, and artwork has been featured in film festivals museum retrospectives, and exhibitions all over the world, including the Museum of Modern Art, the Leslie-Lohman Museum of of Gay and Lesbian Art, and Jeu de Paume. She has won many awards for her work including a Guggenheim Fellowship. Hammer has taught for many years at institutions including the European Graduate School in Saas-Fee, Switzerland.
Content Description
The Barbara Hammer Papers, which span from 1940 to 2017, contain writings, images, research materials, project files, and documentation related to Hammer's films and artwork. The papers also contain personal and professional correspondence, clippings, ephemera, costumes, audiovisual materials, and electronic media related to her life and work.
Documentary films; LGBTQ resource; Filmmakers; Independent filmmakers; Lesbian and gay experience; Lesbianism -- Personal narratives
- Writings and personal papers, 1940-2017; Series I; 22.0; (25 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Materials within this series maintain the original physical organization found at time of acquisition.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains materials related to Barbara Hammer's life including writings, personal and professional correspondence, ephemera, clippings, along with documentation related to her work as a filmmaker.
  - Childhood writings and papers, 1940s - circa 1957 (Box 1)
    Includes: "The Life of Red Flame" typescript; "Smokey" story; "White Monster" story; "Expedition Terror" story; certificate of merit
  - Drawings, circa 1960 - 1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Press clippings, 1960s (Box 1)
    Includes press clippings, some relating to Barbara Hammer.
  - Photos, 1960s - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1960s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1963-1986; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Includes: "a draft & a letter" (1986 February) and letters to mother (1963 September-October)
  - "Influences", circa 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    Includes: newspaper clipings, other typescript and printed papers.
  - Typescript writings about Barbara Hammer, 1976-1979, undated (Box 2)
    Includes: essays about Barbara Hammer and interviews with Barbara Hammer.
  - Programs, circa 1970s (Box 2)
    Includes: programs for events mostly featuring Barbara Hammer.
  - Project notes, circa 1970s (Box 2)
    Includes: project notes; personal notes; program; miscellaneous papers.
  - Photos, circa 1970s (Box 2)
    Includes: photoprints and printed images of and/or by Barbara Hammer.
  - Songs by Barbara Hammer, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    Includes: typed and handwritten lyrics, notation, chords.
  - Influences: Sara Kathryn Alredge, Jane Brakhage, and others, 1969 - circa 1970s (Box 2)
    Includes: folder of papers relating to Sara Kathryn Alredge; small press by others; newspaper and magazine clippings; "Bird Journal" typescript by Jane Brakhage.
  - Releases, circa 1970s (Box 2)
    Includes: hand-signed film releases (permission to appear in Barbara Hammer films).
  - Drawings, poems, and notes, undated (Box 2)
    Includes: Drawings, poems, and notes, some photocopied.
  - Proposals for grant applications, circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, circa 1970s; 6 folders (Box 2)
    Includes: typescript and holograph writings. Folders include "Writings by B.H.", "Writing - Santa Rosa (early 1970's)", "Petaluma / Marie Shaw", "Writing & scripts", "Writing & notes: Petaluma with Marie Shaw", and "Writing (1970's)".
  - Personal letters; project notes, circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Press clippings, circa 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Flyers, programs, promotional materials, circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, 1970s; 4 folders (Box 3)
    Includes: folders titled "Letters to B.H" (x2), "Letters to B.H. from M.H.", and "Letters to barbara (Material for)".
  - Schoolwork from San Francisco State University, circa 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Performances, circa 1970s (Box 3)
    Includes: notes, promotional materials, and newspaper clippings relating to performances, some featuring Barbara Hammer.
  - Contracts, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    Includes: contracts and letters relating to films.
  - Letters from Barbara Hammer, 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - Scripts, 1970s (Box 3)
    Includes: typecript movie scripts by Barbara Hammer.
  - Writings, 1970s; 5 folders (Box 3)
    Includes: folders titled "Miscellaneous writings", "Writing - Notes from Germany", "Writing by B.H." (x2), "Writing - The 'Novel'".
  - Miscellaneous notes, circa 1970s (Box 3)
    Includes: project notes; draft letter to therapist; teaching material; other papers.
  - Promotional materials and programs, circa 1970s (Box 3)
  - Censorship letter, 1978-05-31 (Box 3)
    Includes: letter from Barbara Hammer condemning censorship.
  - "Women & Film" journal issues, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
    Includes: Four issues of "Women & Film".
  - "Dyketypes" performance project notes, circa 1978 (Box 3)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 3)
    Includes: drawings; collage; painting.
  - Project notes for "X" film, undated (Box 3)
  - Press, circa 1977 (Box 3)
    Includes: newspaper clipping and photocopied clipping relating to Barbara Hammer. Also includes notes on audience response to film screening.
  - Sophia Smith Archive correspondence regarding Noel Phyllis Birkby papers, 1978-1997 (Box 3)
    Includes: correspondence between Barbara Hammer and archivist for Sophia Smith Collection; photocopied letters and cards from Barbara Hammer to Phyllis Birkby (1978-1982).
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, 1980s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and call for entries relating to erotic film project, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Letters and cards from others, 1980s, 1999 (Box 4)
    Includes: letters and cards from others; artwork by others; photoprints of Barbara Hammer; promotional material for project by Christine Tamblyn.
  - Press, circa 1987-1988; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Includes three folders--titled "Press", "Press - Photocopies", and "Press - Originals". Folders include newspaper and periodical clippings; photocopied clippings; photocopied journal issue; symposium announcement; holograph notes.
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, 1980s (Box 4)
    Includes: "A Patter of Orgasms" two copies; "Lesbian Studies"; "The Masque of Autonomy"; "The Ritual"; "Touching and Receiving: The Essentials of Lesbian Aesthetic" two copies, one original; "Transcultural Love".
  - Scripts, 1980s (Box 4)
    Includes: "Lesbian Hands"; "Moon Goddess" one original, one copy.
  - "Does Radical Content Deserve Radical Form" panel speeches, 1988-09 (Box 4)
    Includes: typescrpt panel speeches; releases; "Risk-Taking as Alternative Living/Art-Making or Why I Moved to the Big City" typescript.
  - Programs, 1980s; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, 1980s (Box 5)
    Includes: typescript and holograph writings.
  - Photos, 1980s, 1998 (Box 5)
    Includes: photoprints, mostly of Barbara Hammer; printed image; photocopy of drawing with holograph notes.
  - Promotional materials and press, circa 1983-1995 (Box 5)
    Includes: promotional materials for events featuring Barbara Hammer; potocopied newspaper clipping regarding Barbara Hammer.
  - Duplicates, circa 1983-1990 (Box 5)
    Includes: duplicates of promotional materials, programs, photo of Barbara Hammer.
  - Letters from Barbara Hammer, 1980s (Box 5)
    Includes: letters from Barbara Hammer; commercial lists films by Barbara Hammer; Barbara Hammer filmography.
  - Papers and writing regarding Barbara Hammer (Box 5)
    Includes: papers regarding films of Barbara Hammer, typescript; other writing regarding Barbara Hammer, photocopied typescript and photocopied newspaper cliping.
  - Awards, 1982 (Box 6)
    Includes: Cable Car Award for 'Our Trip'; Festival International du Film de Court Metrage et Documenaire, Diploma of Participation for 'Sync Touch'.
  - Censorship, 1985 (Box 6)
    Includes: report of events by Barbara Hammer, photocopied from printed material.
  - Artwork, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes: drawings, collage; photos.
  - Photoprints and printed images, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes: photoprints; printed images; holograph note.
  - Photocopied material for film, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    Folder titled "Bamboo Xerox". Includes: photocopies of photographs, photocopies of plants.
  - Writing, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes: "Some Thoughts on Instiutional Support by a Media Artist" typescript; holograph notes; typescript writing on clear plastic sheet.
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes: letters, cards, postcards; comments on films.
  - Scripts, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes: "Camerawoman" typescript with contact photos and photocopy; holographic text for "Sync Touch"; "The Shadow" typescript; " An Anagogic Tale" typescript; "Screen Play" typescript; "Hot Flash" typescript.
  - Notes, ephemera, and catalog, circa 1979-1981 (Box 6)
  - Proposal and press clippings relating to subway project, circa 1980-1986 (Box 6)
    Includes: project proposal typescript; journal clippings relating to project, some photocopied; festival program.
  - Proposals and applications, circa 1983-1991 (Box 6)
  - Press, circa 1980-1991 (Box 6)
    Incudes: clippings from newpapers and periodicals; photocopied press from newspapers and/or periodicals; typescript wiriting regarding Barbara Hammer.
  - Influences, circa 1979-1989; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Two folders--labelled "Influences" and "Influences - Spiral Mag". Includes: six issues of 'Spiral' magazine; postcards; programs; reviews; periodicals; newspaper clippings; catalogs; other printed material.
  - Programs, 1980s (Box 6)
  - Letters from Barbara Hammer, circa 1981-1990 (Box 6)
    Includes: letters from Barbara Hammer; photocopy of check for film sale; printed image. One letter includes film pasted onto paper.
  - Writings, circa 1980-1989 (Box 6)
    Includes: typescript and printed writings; holograph notes; cards and letters with photoprint; resume.
  - Promotional material and press clipping, circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - Printed material, newspaper clippings, financial material, project notes, circa 1980-1989 (Box 6)
    Original folder labelled "Film Ideas".
  - Contracts, circa 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    Includes: contract; releases; holograph notes.
  - Resume and bibliography, undated, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Ephemera, correspondence, "Experimental Film Congress" declaration, circa 1989 (Box 6)
  - Notebooks and weekly planners, circa 1991-1995 (Box 7)
    Includes: two notebooks; three weekly planners.
  - Materials relating to "Lesbians: Community Cyberspace Biography", circa 1995-1997 (Box 7)
    Includes: promotional material; descriptions of website content; display boards; archive printouts; other items.
  - Personal thank-yous, 1989-1997 (Box 7)
  - Influences, circa 1991-1996 (Box 7)
    Includes: "Super 8" booklet by Anthology Film Archives; postcard series "Sisters of the Harlem Renaissance"; catalogue of programs from New Langton Arts; "Arts Etc" newspaper issue; other printed material.
  - Writings, circa 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    Includes: "Diary for Thursday" for a project by British Film Institute, typescript with holograph corrections; "digital delay", typescript with holograph corrections; "'Truth or Lies': Lesbian Auto/Bio/Graphy", photocopy; printout relating to 'Nitrate Kisses'; associated correspondence.
  - Publications relating to Barbara Hammer, 1991-2001 (Box 7)
    Includes: 'Visible Evidence' volume 9, "Women of Vision: Histories in Feminist Film and Video", photocopy (2001); 'Post Script: Essays in Film and the Humanities' volume 16 no. 3, photocopy (1997); 'Art Papers', photocopy (1991); 'LSD', printed zine (1998). Also includes promotional material for "Lesbian Hands" performance.
  - Printed research materials, 1958-1999 (Box 7)
    Includes: five printed 'Scientific American' articles (1958-1971); "Aperture: The Body in Question" (1990); two periodical newspapers (1999, undated).
  - Grant application materials, 1998-09 (Box 7)
    Includes: materials relating to "Cal Arts Alpert Award in the Arts".
  - Project ideas, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    Includes: project notes; clippings and photocopies of printed material; other papers.
  - Holograph notes for "8 in 8", 1994 (Box 7)
  - Essays regarding Barbara Hammer, 1993-2006 (Box 7)
    Includes: photocopied essays regarding Barbara Hammer, mostly from periodicals.
  - Censorship, 1995-09 (Box 7)
    Includes: fax of packet of papers relating to censorship in San Antonio.
  - "A small gift" box, undated (Box 7)
    Includes: box with film clippings and printed image.
  - "Sanctus" research materials, programs, press releases, circa 1990s; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Press relating to Iraq, circa 2003-2004 (Box 8)
    Includes: clippings, printouts, photocopies. Also includes: materials relating to "Talking About Living Inside the Grid" symposium at New Museum of Contemporary Art with holograph notes.
  - Curriculum vitae additions, 1997, circa 2004 (Box 8)
    Includes: materials relating to events and projects to be included in Barbara Hammer CV.
  - Releases, correspondence, requests for project materials, notes, circa 2001-2007 (Box 8)
  - Research materials and correspondence relating to Julia Pirotte, 2001-2002 (Box 8)
    Includes: printouts, email correspondence.
  - Correspondence, requests, orders, and permissions relating to Bonnie G. Rowan Film Research and National Archives & Records Administration, circa 1999-2002 (Box 8)
  - Documents, notes, and correspondence relating to archival footage, 2001 (Box 8)
  - "The Female Closet" scan list for Staten Island Historical Society, 1997-09 (Box 8)
  - Publications, promotional materials, and other documents relating to Barbara Hammer., circa 1987-2013 (Box 8)
    Includes: publications, promotional materials, and other documents relating to Barbara Hammer, photocopies, clippings, and originals. Also includes: resume and curriculum vitae material for Barbara Hammer.
  - Material relating to "Devotion", circa 1997-2007 (Box 8)
    Includes: correspondence, printed material, and notes relating to "Devotion".
  - Correspondence relating to films by Barbara Hammer, circa 1994-2001 (Box 8)
    Also includes: three documents relating to "Devotion" and "Village of Film: Ogawa Productions".
  - "Tender Fiction" research materials, undated (Box 8)
    Includes: printed images; holograph notes; photocopies of published writings and other materials.
  - Press, undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
    Includes: press clippings and photocopies. Also includes: promotional materials and correspondence.
  - Material relating to "The Female Closet", 1998 (Box 8)
    Includes: press clipings and photocopies; promotional materials; other documents.
  - Awards, acceptance and rejection letters, photocopied press, circa 1995-1998 (Box 8)
  - Programs and promotional materials, circa 1990-1998; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Curation by Barbara Hammer, circa 1996-1998 (Box 9)
    Includes: "Mentor/Mentee", curated by Barbara Hammer; "Mentoring is an Active Verb", curated by Barbara Hammer for MIX 96; "New Film and Video by Barbara Hammer" shorts program; 10th New York Lesbian and Gay Experimental Film/Video Festival program; GLQ Gallery, "Picturing the Modern Amazon", proof of eight visual prints of "Charlene Atlas"
  - Material relating to "Through Black Eyes", 1995 (Box 9)
    Includes: proposal and production notes for "Through Black Eyes".
  - Notebooks, circa 1989-1999 (Box 9)
    Includes: eleven notebooks, one weekly planner.
  - Awards, certificates, releases, letter, circa 1991-1998 (Box 9)
  - Grants, proposals, and applications, circa 1979-1985 (Box 9)
  - Memorials, 1990-1995 (Box 9)
    Includes: invitation and program for memorial for Noel Phyllis Birkby; program for memorial for Vito Russo. Also includes: invitations for parties hosted by Barbara Hammer and Florrie Burke.
  - Programs for events featuring Barbara Hammer, 1994-1998 (Box 9)
  - Material relating to "History Lessons", undated (Box 9)
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, circa 1991-1993 (Box 9)
    Includes: typescript, photocopied, and printed writings.
  - Proposals and applications, circa 1991-1996 (Box 9)
  - Project notes, proposals, correspondence, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 9)
    Includes: notes, proposals, correspondence, and other documents relating to "Nancy Drew Investigates Breast Cancer", "Making Her Visible", and other projects. Also includes: application materials from film crew; Barbara Hammer resume and filmography; other papers.
  - Postcards, promotional material for others, programs, periodicals, circa 1990-1997 (Box 9)
  - Press, 1996-01-1997-03 (Box 9)
    Includes: two copies of Toronto's Lesbian and Gay Biweekly; photocopy of review for "Tender Fictions".
  - Unpublished writing relating to Barbara Hammer, circa 1991-1998 (Box 9)
    Includes: five typescripts relating to Barbara Hammer and her works.
  - Notes, correspondence, and other papers, circa 1991-1993 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, circa 1988-1998; 2 folders (Box 9)
    Twp folders labelled "Mail to Answer" and "Answered Mail". Includes: postcards, cards, and letters. Also includes: holograph notes.
  - Programs, circa 1990s; 3 folders (Box 10)
    Three folders labelled "Programs 1", "Programs 2", and "Programs 3". Also includes: press clippings, correspondence, notes, other papers.
  - Press, 1990s (Box 10)
    Includes: clippings, photocopies, periodicals. Also includes: promotional materials.
  - Writings, circa 1988-1997 (Box 10)
    Includes: typescripts; photocopied printed material; holograph notes.
  - Censorship, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
    Includes: correspondence, holograph notes, and photocopy of printed material relating to censorship.
  - Correspondence, 1990s; (3 folders) (Box 10)
    3 folders labelled "Letters to Barbara Hammer" (x2) and "Letters from Barbara Hammer". Also includes: holograph notes; notebook; other papers.
  - Programs and "Video Guide", circa 1990-1999 (Box 10)
    Includes: programs for film events; "Video Guide" periodical featuring writing by Barbara Hammer.
  - Distribution, circa 1983-1996 (Box 10)
    Includes: materials related to distribution of films; holograph notes.
  - Photos and printed images, circa 1980-1999 (Box 11)
    Includes: personal photoprints; cards including photoprints; printed images relating to Nitrate Kisses; printed images, including a set relating to "Nitrate Kisses"; collage invitation.
  - Materials relating to deafness and HIV/AIDS, circa 1993-1994 (Box 11)
    Includes: letters; newspaper clippings; photocopied printed material; programs; typescript and holograph project notes, including for "The Invisible Disabilities: Deafness and HIV"; other papers.
  - International reviews and promotional materials, circa 1991 (Box 11)
  - Interviews, circa 1995-1998 (Box 11)
    Includes: typescript, printed, and photocopied interviews with Barbara Hammer; correspondence relating to interviews.
  - Programs, promotional materials, and press, circa 1990-1991 (Box 11)
    Includes: programs; newspaper clippings; photocopies; film guide listing of films by Barbara Hammer.
  - "Sanctus" promotional materials, programs, and press, circa 1989-1991 (Box 11)
    Includes: newspaper clippings and photocopies; promotional materials; programs. Also includes: letter relating to research for "Sanctus".
  - "Dr. Watson's X-Rays" project notes, circa 1981-2009 (Box 11)
    Includes: notebook with holograph notes, typescript proposal, other inserted material. Also includes: essay by Christina Lammer relating to "Dr. Watson's X-Rays" and "Sanctus"; other materials.
  - "Out in South Africa" promotional materials, press, and related writings by Barbara Hammer., circa 1995 (Box 11)
    Includes: promotional materials; periodical and periodical clippings; photocopied press; typescript and printed pieces by Barbara Hammer; email printout; Museum of Modern Art program; other papers.
  - Project research and notes, circa 1995-1997 (Box 11)
    Includes: theater and dance programs; commercial mail; holograph notes; menu; exhibition proposal for "First Memories"; newspaper clippings; letter to Helen Mirren; letter fragment; photocopied information sheet for "Turbulent Arts".
  - "Nothing Could Be Worse Than Two Dykes in Menopause" project, circa 1996 (Box 11)
    Includes: scripts, project notes, and application for "Nothing Could Be Worse Than Two Dykes in Menopause"; script for "Spark" by Garret C. Williams; newspaper clippings relating to potential actors for "Nothing Could Be Worse Than Two Dykes in Menopause"; photocopied syllabus for screenwriting class.
  - Papers relating to "Sodom's Lot" and the Philippines, circa 1985-1997 (Box 11)
    Includes: material relating to "Sodom's Lot" project; research materials relating to "Lot in Sodom" by Dr. James Sibley Watson; letters from and papers relating to Wilhelmina Orozco; material relating to the Philippines, including travel grant application, correspondence, newspaper, brochure, and flyer.
  - University of Nebraska brochures, undated (Box 11)
    Includes: brochures for "The Films of Barbara Hammer" showcase event at University of Nebraska.
  - Event programs, 1994-1996 (Box 11)
    Also includes: short piece by Barbara Hammer about experimental film, with holograph notes on back.
  - Flyers and letter from France, circa 1992 (Box 11)
  - Day planner, 1997 (Box 11)
  - Programs, circa 2000s; 3 folders (Box 12)
    Two folders labelled "Programs 1" and "Programs 2". Also includes: press clippings and photocopies; printed periodicals; promotional materials; personal papers relating to travel; other papers.
  - Material relating to "Our Grief Is Not a Cry for War", 2003-2004 (Box 12)
    Includes: typescripts relating to "Our Grief Is Not a Cry for War". Also includes: flyer for event featuring Barbara Hammer.
  - Papers relating to panels, conferences, and other events featuring Barbara Hammer, circa 2000-2002 (Box 12)
    Includes: program, promotional material, speech, and other papers relating to "Persisten Vision" conference; flyers; programs; letter and emails relating to events featuring Barbara Hammer; holograph notes; other papers.
  - Writings about Barbara Hammer, 1996-2004 (Box 12)
    Includes: typescript with photocopied holograph notes; photocopies of printed material; online printouts.
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, circa 1997-2005 (Box 12)